Dr. Steven R. Goldman

Software Engineer II · Space Telescope Science Institute 3700 San Martin Drive Baltimore, MD 21218 sgoldman@stsci.edu

Research Interests: The effects of metallicity on the dust production, wind dynamics, mass-loss mechanism, and evolution of Asymptotic Giant Branch stars and Red Supergiants.

APPOINTMENTS

Science Software Engineer, STScI	February 2023 - present
Visiting Assistant Professor, Haverford College, PA	January 2023 - May 2023
Observatory & Instrument Scientist, SOFIA	November 2021 - February 2023
Postdoctoral Fellow, STScI	October 2017 - November 2021

EDUCATION

PhD in Astrophysics Keele University, UK

October 2013 - December 2017

- o Advisor: Jacco Th. van Loon
- Thesis: The metallicity dependence of maser emission and mass loss from red supergiants and asymptotic giant branch stars
- B. S. in Physics St. Lawrence University, USA

September 2009 - July 2013

AWARDED PROPOSALS (PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR)

2022 Hubble Space Telescope, PID: 17088 (\$137 k)	30 primary orbits
2022 SOFIA (first quintile)	18 hours (canceled)
2022 GASKAP-OH (Science team lead: LMC maser populations	s) 50 hours
2021 Hubble Space Telescope, PID: 16492 (\$65 k)	4 primary orbits
2021 SOFIA, PID: 75_0057 (\$40 k)	4 hours
2017 Australia Telescope Compact Array Telescope, PID: C2996	92 hours
2017 Very Large Telescope VISIR, PID: 099.D-0907	1 Night
2017 Very Large Telescope VISIR, PID: 098.D-0272	0.5 hours
2016 Very Large Telescope XSHOOTER, PID: 097.D-0605	1.5 hours
2015 Westerbork Synthesis Radio Telescope, PID: R14/010	30 hours
2014 Southern African Large Telescope	5.5 hours

RECENT AWARDED PROPOSALS (CO-INVESTIGATOR)

James Webb Space Telescope (3 programs)	72 primary / 2 parallel hours
Hubble Space Telescope (9 programs)	120 primary / 535 parallel orbits
SOFIA (2 programs)	20.25 hours
SOFIA Legacy (cut short by cancellation)	$100 \text{ hours} \rightarrow 4 \text{ hours}$
ACA (NESS)	750 hours
Astrophysics Data Analysis Program (18-ADAI	P18-142) \$335 k
ALMA	5 hours

SELECTED SEMINAR & CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

2024 Talk, AAS Winter Meeting New Orleans, USA 2022 Invited Speaker, IAU General Assembly Busan, South Korea 2022 Featured Speaker, AstroPhilly22 Villanova University, USA 2022 Invited Colloquim University of Auckland, New Zealand 2022 Invited Colloquim Auckland University of Technology, New Zealand 2022 Invited Colloquim University of Canterbury, New Zealand Pasadena, USA 2022 Invited Talk, AAS Summer Meeting 2022 Invited Colloquim NRC Herzberg, Canada 2022 Poster, SOFIA Lake Arrowhead Conference, CA, USA 2021 Invited Panelist, Evolved Stars and their Circumstellar Environments Global (Remote) 2021 Invited Talk, GAPS: unsolved problems in red Giants And suPergiantS Global (Remote) 2021 Talk, DELVE: The Death-Throes of Evoled Stars Global (Remote) 2021 Invited Talk St. Lawrence University, USA 2020 Invited Talk STScI, USA 2020 Poster, AAS Winter Meeting Honolulu, USA 2019 Invited Colloquim RIT, USA 2019 Invited Colloquim EAO Hawaii, USA 2019 Talk, A Star Has Evolved: A Conference in the Honor of Hans Olofsson Smögen, Sweden 2019 Talk, HotSci STScI, USA 2019 Poster, AAS Winter Meeting Seattle, USA 2018 Poster, IAU General Assembly Vienna, Austria 2018 Talk, Cosmic Dust: origin, applications & implications Copenhagen, Denmark 2018 Talk, European Week in Astronomy and Space Science Liverpool, UK 2016 Talk, Blowing in the wind (Awarded Best Talk) ICISE, Vietnam 2016 Talk, Postgraduate Research Symposium (Awarded Best Talk) Keele University, UK 2016 Talk, SKA Delivering the Science Cambridge University, UK 2015 Talk, UK SKA Science Meeting Manchester University, UK 2015 Poster, Stellar End Products: The low mass - high mass connection ESO, Germany Kagoshima University, Japan 2015 Invited Colloquim,

TEACHING & MENTORING

Courses Taught:

Visiting Assistant Professor, Astro 101, Haverford College, (Spring 2023)

Demonstrator/Lab Assistant, *Electronics*, Keele University (2014-2016)

Demonstrator/Lab Assistant, Programming I, Keele University (2015)

Students Mentored:

Tessa Pearlstein Haverford College, Summer 2023

Dust Injection Rate of TP-AGB stars in the M33

Sean Garner SOFIA/USRA, Summer 2022

SOFIA/EXES Water Line Analysis of the Symbiotic Mira HM Sge

Nathan Wolthuis SOFIA/USRA, Summer 2022

HST/WFC3 Image Analysis of Nebular NII emission of HM Sge

OBSERVING EXPERIENCE

3 flights
70 hours
1 night
92 hours
36 hours
20 hours

SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENT 🖸

Observatory Service

- *Drizzlepac*: Primary maintainer for the widely-used image re-alignment software used for the Hubble Space Telescope pipeline mosaicing.
- SOFIA Data-Analysis Cookbooks and FAQs: Jupyter notebooks demonstrating a variety of techniques for analyzing infrared data from SOFIA, as well as detailed explanations FAQs of common misconceptions.

Research

- The *DESK*: Independently led the development and publication of the first open-source python package to fit the light and colors of evolved stars with models to get meaningful properties.
- \circ The *BEAST*: Improved on testing and functionality of a large-scale open-source astropy-affiliated python package with a large team with different levels of coding experience.

PRESS & OUTREACH

Sky at Night magazine interview about SOFIA New Zealand deployment NASA press release, SOFIA Watches a Binary Star System's Eclipse

Virtual Community Outreach, 2018-Present, (USA, Canada, & Mexico)

• Skype-a-Scientist, NASA's Universe of Learning, independently organized

Earth and Space Observatory volunteer, 2013–2017, (Keele University, UK)

AWARDED FELLOWSHIPS

2015 E. A. Milne Traveling Fellowship (£ 2500)

2012 National Science Foundation Summer REU Fellowship

ACADEMIC SERVICE

Organized and gave the SOFIA New Zealand Lecture Series	July 2022
SOFIA School Co-Chair	February 2022
STScI postdoctoral representative	2020 - 2022
Bystander Intervention Workshop	March 2021
DELVE conference SOC	February 2021
Low-Density Universe Lunch Organizer	2018 - 2019

TAC Panel Support: Hubble & SOFIA

Referee: Astrophysical Journal; Astronomy & Astrophysics

Links: ADS, ORCID, Google Scholar

REFEREED PUBLICATIONS

First-Authored Peer-Reviewed Publications:

- Goldman S. R. et al., 2023, ApJ, submitted
 A Multi-Wavelength Study of the Symbiotic Mira HM Sge with SOFIA & HST
- 2. Goldman S. R. et al., 2022, ApJS, 259, 41 citations: 4
 A Census of Thermally-Pulsing AGB stars in the Andromeda Galaxy and a First Estimate of their
 Contribution to the Global Dust Budget
- 3. Goldman S. R., 2020, JOSS, 5(54), 2554 citations: 6
 The Dusty Evolved Star Kit (DESK): A Python package for fitting the Spectral Energy Distribution of Evolved Stars. Journal of Open Source Software
- 4. Goldman S. R. et al., 2019, ApJ, 884, 152 AGB Stars in the Nearby Galaxy: Leo P
- 5. Goldman S. R. et al., 2019, ApJ, 877, 49 citations: 26
 An Infrared Census Of Dust In Nearby Galaxies With Spitzer (DUSTiNGS): V. The Periodluminosity Relation For Dusty Metal-poor AGB Stars
- 6. Goldman S. R. et al., 2018, MNRAS, 473, 3835 citations: 15 A dearth of OH/IR stars in the Small Magellanic Cloud
- 7. Goldman S. R. et al., 2017, MNRAS, 465, 403 citations: 117 The wind speeds, dust content, and mass-loss rates of evolved AGB and RSG stars at varying metallicity

Co-Authored Peer-Reviewed Publications:

- 8. Mull et al. 2022, ApJ, 941, 206
 A Panchromatic Study of Massive Stars in the Extremely Metal-Poor Local Group Dwarf Galaxy
 Leo A
- 9. Ingallinera et al. 2022, MNRAS, 512, 21
 Evolutionary map of the Universe (EMU): 18-cm OH-maser discovery in ASKAP continuum images of the SCORPIO field
- 10. Sankrit et al. 2022, ApJ, 926, 177

 SOFIA/FORCAST Monitoring of the Dust Emission from R Agr: Start of the Eclipse
- 11. Scicluna et al. 2022, MNRAS, 512, 1091

 The Nearby Evolved Stars Survey II: Constructing a volume-limited sample and first results from the James Clerk Maxwell Telescope
- 12. Jones et al., 2021, MNRAS, 504, 565

 Infrared variable stars in the compact elliptical galaxy M32
- 13. Girardi et al., 2020, ApJ, 901, 19
 PHAT XX. AGB stars and other cool giants in M31 star clusters

- 14. Nanni A. et al., 2019, MNRAS, 487, 502
 - The mass-loss, expansion velocities and dust production rates of carbon stars in the Magellanic Clouds
- 15. Dharmawardena T. E. et al., 2019, MNRAS, 489, 3218

 The Nearby Evolved Stars Survey: I. JCMT/SCUBA-2 Sub-millimetre detection of the detached shell of U Antliae
- Karambelkar V. R. et al., 2019, ApJ, 877, 110
 SPIRITS Catalog of Infrared Variables: Identification of Extremely Luminous Long Period Variables
- 17. Orosz G. et al., 2017, AJ, 153, 1190

 Astrometry of OH/IR stars using 1612 MHz hydroxyl masers. I. Annual parallaxes of WX Psc and OH138.0+7.2
- 18. Groenewegen M. A. T. et al., 2016, A&A, 596, A50

 The ALMA detection of CO rotational line emission in AGB stars in the Large Magellanic Cloud
- 19. McDonald I. et al., 2015, MNRAS, 453, 4324 ALMA reveals sunburn: CO dissociation around AGB stars in the globular cluster 47 Tucanae

Other Publications:

- 20. Goldman et al. 2022, Research Notes of the AAS, 6, 159 Sudden Dimming of the Symbiotic Mira HM Sge
- 21. Goldman et al. 2022, AAS Meeting, 240 proceedings, 426.04

 A Census of Thermally-Pulsing AGB stars in the Andromeda Galaxy and a First Estimate of their Contribution to the Global Dust Budget
- 22. Sloan et al. 2021, AAS Meeting, 237 proceedings, 541.16 Spitzer's Last Look at the Small Magellanic Cloud.
- 23. Scicluna et al. 2020, arXiv:2002.03100 (Decadal white paper)

 Studies of Evolved Stars in the Next Decade: EAO Submillimetre Futures White Paper Series
- 24. Karambelkar et al. 2020, , AAS Meeting, 235 proceedings, 335.04 SPIRITS catalog of infrared variables : Identification of extremely luminous long period variables
- 25. Goldman S. R. and Boyer M. L., 2019, IAU Meeting 343 proceedings, 14(S343), 406-408 Infrared light curves of dusty & metal-poor AGB stars
- 26. Goldman S. R. and Boyer M. L., 2019, AAS Meeting 233 proceedings, 33.06 Infrared light curves of dusty & metal-poor AGB stars